<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jeff Keiser</title>
    <description>JeffKeiser.com explores the Bible, Christianity, and culture from a scholarly perspective. The site is currently under construction, so check back regularly for updates.
</description>
    <link>http://jeffkeiser.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jeffkeiser.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 09:46:20 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 09:46:20 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is the Coding Revolution Really Revolutionary?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The current issue of &lt;em&gt;Scientific American&lt;/em&gt; (Aug 2016) includes an article entitled “The Coding Revolution,” on the push to teach coding to K–12 kids. How revolutionary is this movement? Consider the following quotations from proponents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Computational thinking includes the ability to abstract, to engage in logical and symbolic reasoning, to take a big problem and decompose it into many smaller problems… These are skills that everyone can use, whether they’re using a computer or not.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This is about teaching habits of mind that can be used to solve problems in any realm—habits like breaking down a problem into its component parts, running small experiments to see which approaches fail and which succeed, and working together with other people to find and apply the best ideas.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We’re teaching kids to be problem solvers, to think logically, to engage in abstract thinking, to find patterns, to identify alternatives.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Because students are encountering the same mental tools across many different courses, they come to see how universally applicable they are, even outside of school.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound familiar? That’s because similar claims appear time and again in discussions about the value of teaching the humanities. Replace “computational thinking” or “coding” with “critical thinking” and the arguments are basically the same in both realms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article tacitly acknowledges that the gains these proponents of K–12 coding see in their students come from progressive engagement with ever more complex problems over time and not from computational theory or coding as such. The problems are content specific, but the outcomes are not. This means that similar outcomes can be achieved in different disciplines, such as, say, literature or philosophy, through progressive engagement with the ever more complex content over time. How revolutionary!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/is-the-coding-revolution-really-revolutionary</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/is-the-coding-revolution-really-revolutionary</guid>
        
        <category>Coding</category>
        
        <category>Science</category>
        
        <category>Humanities</category>
        
        <category>Pedagogy</category>
        
        <category>Education</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Memory Eternal: Ellen Bradshaw Aitken (1961–2014)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: left; width: 150px; margin-right: 1em;&quot; title=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;http://publications.mcgill.ca/reporter/files/2014/06/aitken_090826-111252-5232.web_.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;οἱ ὀρθῶς φιλοσοφοῦντες ἀποθνῄσκειν μελετῶσι&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“True philosophers are always preparing to die” (Socrates, in Plato’s &lt;em&gt;Phaedo&lt;/em&gt; 67e).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt.start--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ellen Bradshaw Aitken, my advisor, friend, and mentor, died early in the morning on Saturday, June 14. Her death was graceful and peaceful, as was her life.&lt;!--excerpt.end--&gt; Many of her friends, colleagues, and students have shared memories of Ellen on her Facebook page, which now serves as a fitting memorial to a life well-lived. This is true because Ellen was always enthusiastic about the possibilities of scholarship in the digital age, but especially because memorials are as much for the living as for the dead. We ‘share’ and ‘like’ to support each other, so I want to do my small part in preserving her memory among the living by sharing my experiences of her life—and her death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My relationship with Ellen was always serendipitous. I first met her in 2002, when I was a master’s student at Harvard. As my de facto advisor for matters related to the study of the New Testament, she gently answered my naïve questions about the value of historical scholarship. She did not have to take the time for this, but she did—always. When I was considering Ph.D. programs several years later, after she had moved on to McGill, she suggested that I apply there. I am embarrassed to say that neither McGill nor Montréal had been on my rader before that moment, but the decision was easy. Over the next nine years, in addition to regular meetings in her office or over lunch, we would have many chance conversations in the foyer of the Birks building at McGill. I vividly recall one such conversation, in which she explained with a warm smile that she need only stand in a certain spot for a short while and whomever she wanted to see would invariably pass by. Call me superstitious, if you like, but I believe that she is standing in that very spot right now, smiling warmly and waiting to see whomever she wants to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even my thesis topic seems to have come to me serendipitously, although in truth I had long been wondering how best to integrate Ellen’s interests into my own scholarship. I recently explained this to an inteview committee during a coveted campus visit (I did not get the job), and one or two members chuckled, as if it were a strange and amusing thing for a newly-minted Ph.D. to express such concern to carry on his or her advisor’s work. They did not know Ellen. Everyone who knew Ellen also knows that they owe her a debt of gratitude for her patience, her gracious and diplomatic manner, and—especially for students and former students like me—her tireless advocacy. That is how she lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I visited Ellen twice in the hospital before she died. The first time she was tired but lucid. She looked well for someone who had recently undergone a nine-hour surgery. She explained that she had been anointed several times (for healing), and that she and her husband, Bill, were starting to think about end-of-life matters. I prattled on nervously about a newly ordained priest at the parish I attend and about a paper I had just given. The second time I visited her she was in the ICU for treatment of the infection that would hasten her death. She was awake and aware of my presence but unable to talk very easily since her breathing tube had only recently been removed. I held her hand tightly but said little, not knowing what to say. Then she showed me a small boat of sculpted marble resting on her lap. Bill explained, at her request, that they had seen a similar boat at a funeral they had attended (sadly, I forget whose funeral). Each person at this funeral was asked to breath into this boat, which was later buried with the deceased. Ellen put the little boat into my hand and asked me to breath into it. As I did, the image of an Orthodox priest breathing three times over the waters of a baptismal font appeared to me—strange but somehow appropriate. I have since thought also of the Ferryman of souls, Charon, from classical Greek culture. Whatever the association, what stands out most in my memory is this simple and beautiful ritual. When I could not find the words to say goodbye, Ellen provided a way forward. That is how she faced death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Socrates is right—if true philosophers are always preparing to die—then the highest compliment I can pay to Ellen is that she was a true philosopher. This is true because of the graceful way in which lived and the graceful way in which she faced a vicious illness, but above all it is true because of the graceful way in which she prepared others for her death. I know, too, that Ellen would appreciate the fact that the role of Socrates is taken over by a woman, Macrina the Younger, in the Orthodox Christian tradition. Gregory of Nyssa calls Macrina Teacher—διδάσκαλος—for her fortitude in the face of death. It seems fitting, then, to dedicate Macrina’s words to my Teacher, whom I pray is free from all pain and suffering in the God who is Love:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Love is the foremost of all all excellent acheivements and the first of the commandments of the law. If ever, then, the soul reach this goal, it will be in no need of anything else . . . For the life of the Supreme Being is love . . . ” (Macrina the Younger, in Gregory of Nyssa’s &lt;em&gt;Dialogue on the Soul and the Resurrection&lt;/em&gt; [J.-P. Migne, &lt;em&gt;Patrologia Graeca&lt;/em&gt; 46.96–97]).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2014 14:04:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/memory-eternal-ellen-bradshaw-aitken</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/memory-eternal-ellen-bradshaw-aitken</guid>
        
        <category>Philosophy</category>
        
        <category>Ellen Aitken</category>
        
        <category>Gregory of Nyssa</category>
        
        <category>Death</category>
        
        <category>Macrina the Younger</category>
        
        <category>Dying</category>
        
        <category>Phaedo</category>
        
        <category>Socrates</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Saint Paul, Conversion, and Social Constructionism</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 1em;&quot; title=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;http://irrco.files.wordpress.com/2010/11/stpaul.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ravenna Paul&quot; width=&quot;100px&quot; height=&quot;100px&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt.start--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several weeks ago I met with a few friends for an ongoing discussion of William James’s classic Gifford Lectures, &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/20080727010425/http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/toc/modeng/public/JamVari.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Varieties of Religious Experience&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. One of our criticisms of James concerns his assumption that psychological phenomena recur unchanged over millennia. This came up again in our discussion of James’s lectures on conversion. As a New Testament scholar, I wondered why James skips lightly over Saint Paul’s conversion.&lt;!--excerpt.end--&gt; James calls it “the most eminent” of those “striking, instantaneous instances” of conversion, but refrains from analyzing it in much detail. This is significant because Paul’s conversion has provided a template for other conversions throughout the history of Christianity. It is also significant because, in recent decades, scholars have debated the conditions of Paul’s about-face from persecutor of the church to preacher of Jesus as the Christ. A consensus has formed around the view that Paul did not—indeed &lt;em&gt;could not&lt;/em&gt;—convert from Judaism to Christianity, but from Pharisaic Judaism to an apocalyptic, messianic sect of Judaism. The debate continues over the question of whether this conversion was truly instantaneous or whether it was the culmination of prior social and psychological processes. This question is complicated by the fact that our only accounts of the event come from Paul’s own letters, written some twenty years later, and the second-hand reports in the Acts of the Apostles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I see it, there are at least three ways to frame the issue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paul’s experience was preconditioned by his formation as a Pharisee and/or other factors related to his Jewish upbringing, and is fully explicable within that context; only later did he identify Jesus with the apocalyptic son of God who had been revealed to him in the environs of Damascus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paul’s experience was preconditioned by his knowledge of the emergent Jesus movement and his fraught encounters with its members; he may not have been looking for a revelation of Jesus, but he was psychologically prepared for the event.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nothing or next to nothing in Paul’s background prepared him for the event, although he presses his background into service, at times, in order to articulate his present commitment to Jesus in the starkest possible contrast to his checkered past.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two positions are mutually compatible, in part because they both presuppose that conversion is a socially constructed phenomenon, and in part because Pharisees and the earliest followers of Jesus coexisted as first-century Jewish sects. As yet, there was no such thing as Christianity. The third position approximates James’s notion that Paul’s conversion exemplifies a distinctive, transhistorical variety of religious experience—the instantaneous conversion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say that conversion is socially constructed is to acknowledge the power of language to shape social realities. As an Evangelical convert to Eastern Orthodox Christianity, my own experience provides a kind of case study. My conversion did not take place instantaneously in a blinding flash of light, but only after many months of reading, praying, and searching for what I hoped would be an intellectually and spiritually deeper experience of church. I was frustrated with the vapid homogeneity of Southern California’s Evangelical churches, where a typical worship service consists of 45 minutes of repetitive praise songs and a 45 minute, rhetorical roller-coaster of a sermon with a final call to “ask Jesus into your heart” or “make Jesus your personal Lord and Savior.” The parody of such services in the video below is spot-on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;videoWrapper-16-9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/3RJBd8zE48A&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my conversion I read enough Evangelical-to-Eastern Orthodox literature and encountered enough converts from Evangelical Christianity to learn that we all have similar stories, despite differing emphases. At one point this bothered me so much that I stopped calling myself a convert. I have since come to appreciate the fact that such recycling of stories is unavoidable and even necessary for the formation and maintenance of likeminded communities. For converts to the ethnically-constituted churches of Eastern Orthodoxy—Greek, Russian, Arabic, and so on—these stories help us to bond with each other and to establish a distinctive identity in parishes that are still largely defined by family ties and cultural commitments that, to be frank, do not always coincide with our own. In short, our stories shape our social reality within communities that continue to generate considerable barriers to entry and considerable cultural dissonance thereafter. The relative homogeneity of these stories does not point to a transhistorical variety of religious experience but to the historical experiences of particular people who share a particular set of circumstances and, for reasons that are probably beyond our ken, collectively choose to represent those experiences in a particular way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what does all this have to do with Saint Paul? He was not the first Jew to conclude that Jesus is the Christ, nor even the first Jew to invite non-Jews to participate in this new community of likeminded believers, so it is reasonable to suppose that his conversion story was influenced both by his past and by the lost stories of others in his adoptive community. Still, James’s notion of relgious ‘geniuses’ makes me wonder whether one person’s story can be so compelling as to change the narrative for everyone who follows in his or her footsteps. Were we to identify Paul’s conversion story as just such a story, would this imply that his experience was indeed &lt;em&gt;sui generis&lt;/em&gt;—unprecedented—or only that his peculiar genius lay in his manner of presentation?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2014 16:08:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/saint-paul-conversion-and-social-constructionism</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/saint-paul-conversion-and-social-constructionism</guid>
        
        <category>William James</category>
        
        <category>Evangelicalism</category>
        
        <category>Paul</category>
        
        <category>Social Constructionism</category>
        
        <category>Conversion</category>
        
        <category>Orthodoxy</category>
        
        <category>Religious Experience</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quote of the Day</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“The wise person is not self-mastered but moderate, nor does the fool lack self-mastery but moderation. For the one takes pleasure in what is honourable, while the other is not troubled by shameful things. Lack of self-mastery, therefore, is the mark of a sophistic soul having reason but not the ability to stand by the things that it has correctly discerned” (Plutarch, &lt;em&gt;On Moral Virtue&lt;/em&gt; 446c).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 14:42:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/quote-of-the-day-plutarch-on-moral-virtue-446c</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/quote-of-the-day-plutarch-on-moral-virtue-446c</guid>
        
        <category>Plutarch</category>
        
        <category>moderation</category>
        
        <category>self-mastery</category>
        
        <category>Quote of the Day</category>
        
        <category>enkrateia</category>
        
        <category>akrasia</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quote of the Day</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Clemency is the mark of a good ruler, but lack of severity is the mark of a bad philosopher” (Dio Chrysostom, &lt;em&gt;Alexander&lt;/em&gt; 32.18).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry, Plato. If Dio is right, either a good king will be a bad philosopher or a bad king will be a good philosopher.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2012 10:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/quote-of-the-day-dio-chrysostom-alexander-32-18</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/quote-of-the-day-dio-chrysostom-alexander-32-18</guid>
        
        <category>Philosophy</category>
        
        <category>Politics</category>
        
        <category>Plato</category>
        
        <category>Quote of the Day</category>
        
        <category>Dio Chrysostom</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quote of the Day</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“The poetry of the sane person is eclipsed by that of inspired manics” (Plato, &lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt; 245a)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know why I’m such a bad poet&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 08:58:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/quote-of-the-day-plato-phaedrus-245a</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/quote-of-the-day-plato-phaedrus-245a</guid>
        
        <category>madness</category>
        
        <category>Plato</category>
        
        <category>Quote of the Day</category>
        
        <category>Poetry</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on Theosis, Part 3: Theosis and Orthodox Doctrine</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Other posts in this series:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-1&quot;&gt;Part 1: Vocabulary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-2&quot;&gt;Part 2: What the Bible Says About Theosis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theosis is less a doctrine than a practical outworking of the doctrine of the Incarnation.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In that sense it is a response to the question posed most famously by Anselm of Canterbury, but already a millenium old before he formulated it: &lt;em&gt;Cur deus homo?&lt;/em&gt; Why the God-Man? Anselm proposed that human beings had violated God’s honor and consequently incurred a debt that no one could possibly repay. By taking on human flesh and voluntarily suffering a penalty he did not deserve, Jesus not only satisfied that debt but stored up a treasury of merit that far exceeded any future debt: &lt;a href=&quot;/anselm-on-the-atonement&quot;&gt;the gift that keeps on giving&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anselm’s theory of satisfaction set an important precedent for later conceptions of the Incarnation and Atonement in Western Christendom, but it is neither the only nor the earliest response to the question posed by the Incarnation. According to Irenaeus of Lyons, Jesus Christ is “the only true and steadfast teacher, the Word of God … [who] became what we are in order to draw us to himself” (&lt;em&gt;Against Heresies&lt;/em&gt; 5, Introduction). Clement of Alexandria says that “the Word of God became human so that you may learn from a human how a human may become god” (&lt;em&gt;Exhortation to the Greeks&lt;/em&gt; 1.8.4). Similar sayings abound in the Fathers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt.start--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of teaching and discipleship provides a helpful way to think about theosis. For many of the Eastern Fathers the Incarnation teaches not only that human nature &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be deified but that deification is ultimately what God intended for human beings.&lt;!--excerpt.end--&gt; I looked at some of the key scriptures supporting this view in my &lt;a href=&quot;/thoughts-on-theosis-part-2&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, but more can be said about how the Fathers read the Bible through the lens of the Incarnation. This Christological way of to reading is especially remarkable in certain early interpretations of Genesis 1, where the acts of creation are understood not merely as past events but also as anticipating the &lt;em&gt;future&lt;/em&gt; perfection of God’s creatures. “God does not judge the beauty of His work by the charm of the eyes,” says Saint Basil the Great:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;and He does not form the same idea of beauty that we do. What He esteems beautiful is that which presents in its perfection all the fitness of art, and that which tends to the usefulness of its end. He, then, who proposed to Himself a manifest design in His works, approved each one of them, as fulfilling its end in accordance with His creative purpose (&lt;em&gt;Homilies on the Six Days of Creation&lt;/em&gt; 3.10)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Greek text of Basil’s Bible, God does not see that what he has created is merely ‘good’ but that it is literally ‘beautiful’. Beauty is in the eye of the Beholder, says Basil, and what God beholds is the final perfection of his creatures. Elsewhere Basil describes creation as “both a school and a training ground where the souls of human beings should be taught, and a home for beings destined to be born and to die” (&lt;em&gt;Homilies on the Six Days of Creation&lt;/em&gt; 1.5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this world in which we live is both a school and a training ground, then who is our Instructor? Ignatius of Antioch celebrates Jesus as the &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; person who perfectly demonstrates the integrity of words and deeds thought to be a key virtue of successful teachers. For Ignatius, Jesus is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; example for all who desire to teach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is good to teach, if the one who speaks also acts. There was one Teacher who &lt;em&gt;spoke&lt;/em&gt; and it happened. And the things he has &lt;em&gt;done&lt;/em&gt; while remaining silent are worthy of the Father.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The one who truly possesses the word of Jesus is able even to hear his silence (&lt;em&gt;hesychia&lt;/em&gt;), so that he may be perfect, so that he may act through his speech and be understood through his silence. Nothing escapes the notice of the Lord, but even the things we hide are near to him. Therefore we should do everything as though he were dwelling in us, that we may be his temples and he our God in us, as in fact he is, and he will appear before our eyes. For which reasons let us love him justly (&lt;em&gt;To the Ephesians&lt;/em&gt; 15.1–3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of Orthodox &lt;em&gt;hesychasts&lt;/em&gt; (those who practice what is called the prayer of the heart) is not merely to know God abstractly, through doctrinal or theological propositions, but truly to &lt;em&gt;possess&lt;/em&gt; the word of Jesus and to hear His silence, to unify speech and action so perfectly that they pray unceasingly (1 Thess 5:17) and even without words (Rom 8:26–27), and finally to see the deifying light of the Transfiguration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Despite the title of Norman Russell’s indispensable survey of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Doctrine-Deification-Patristic-Tradition-Christian/dp/0199205973?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=sacrveil-20&amp;amp;link_code=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&quot;&gt;The Doctrine of Deification in the Greek Patristic Tradition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On the speech and silence of Jesus in this passage, see my forthcoming essay: “Hearing God’s Silence: Ignatius of Antioch and the Music of the Spheres” in ed. Ellen Aitken and John Fossey, &lt;em&gt;Late Antique Crossroads in the Levant&lt;/em&gt; (full publication information to follow). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2010 21:52:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-3</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-3</guid>
        
        <category>Clement of Alexandria</category>
        
        <category>Basil the Great</category>
        
        <category>Deification</category>
        
        <category>Hesychasm</category>
        
        <category>Genesis</category>
        
        <category>Ignatius of Antioch</category>
        
        <category>Incarnation</category>
        
        <category>Jesus</category>
        
        <category>Theosis</category>
        
        <category>Irenaeus of Lyons</category>
        
        <category>Anselm</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on Theosis, Part 2: What the Bible Says about Theosis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Other posts in this series:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-1&quot;&gt;Part 1: Vocabulary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-3&quot;&gt;Part 3: Theosis and Orthodox Doctrine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contemporary Orthodox theologians sometimes pay more attention to the doctrinal foundations of theosis than to its biblical roots. This is less a symptom of neglect than a consequence of the fact that the Fathers &lt;em&gt;did not&lt;/em&gt; neglect the Bible in their doctrinal formulations. Neither feeling the need nor the desire to reinvent the wheel, contemporary theologians usually head straight for what may well be the most memorable and oft-repeated of Patristic sayings: “God became man so that man might become god.” Athanasius of Alexandria is the favorite authority for this saying (&lt;em&gt;On the Incarnation&lt;/em&gt; 54.3), but one also finds nods to Irenaeus of Lyons and Clement of Alexandria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irenaus, Clement, and Athanasius link “becoming god” with the prior event of God becoming human—the Incarnation. I’ll have more to say about this connection later, but for now it suffices to say that these Fathers provide the simplest &lt;em&gt;conceptual&lt;/em&gt; definition of theosis—“becoming god.” They do not use the actual word &lt;em&gt;theosis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither the word &lt;em&gt;theosis&lt;/em&gt; nor &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of the technical words and phrases typically used to express the concept have direct equivalents in the Bible.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The closest biblical parallel to the idea of &lt;em&gt;participation&lt;/em&gt; in God is 2 Peter’s reference to becoming &lt;em&gt;sharers&lt;/em&gt; of the divine nature through the glory and excellence of Jesus (2 Pet 1:4),&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but the Fathers rarely cite this passage.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;!--excerpt.start--&gt;The most frequently cited text in discussions of becoming god is Psalm 82:6 (81:6 in the Septuagint, the Greek translation of the Hebrew scriptures). A single verse is admittedly a weak foundation for an entire tradition, even by the standards of patristic exegesis, so let’s look more closely at this psalm in its historical, canonical, and traditional contexts.&lt;!--excerpt.end--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its original historical setting Psalm 82 may have had in view one of several possible scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The assembly of gods (Psalm 82:1 TNIV) could represent a council of divine beings who are truly gods. Such scenes are common in Ancient Near Eastern literature, less so in the Hebrew Bible. In this case the Psalm would envision a council of gods who are &lt;em&gt;essentially&lt;/em&gt; equals but &lt;em&gt;administratively&lt;/em&gt; subordinate to the presiding God of Israel.&amp;lt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The assembly of gods could represent a council of angelic beings like the “sons of God” mentioned in the book of Job (&lt;cite style=&quot;font-style: normal&quot; title=&quot;Job 1:6&quot; class=&quot;bibleref&quot;&gt;1:6&lt;/cite&gt;; &lt;cite style=&quot;font-style: normal&quot; title=&quot;Job 2:1&quot; class=&quot;bibleref&quot;&gt;2:1&lt;/cite&gt;; &lt;cite style=&quot;font-style: normal&quot; title=&quot;Job 38:7&quot; class=&quot;bibleref&quot;&gt;38:7&lt;/cite&gt;). In this case they would not be considered gods in the same sense as the God of Israel, being both &lt;em&gt;essentially&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;administratively&lt;/em&gt; subordinate to the God of Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The assembly of gods could represent a council of &lt;em&gt;earthly&lt;/em&gt; authorities who bear the title ‘gods’ by virtue of their official status as earthly counterparts to heavenly rulers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whoever or whatever these ‘gods’ are, the God of Israel appears to hold them directly responsible for the plight of the poor and oppressed (&lt;cite style=&quot;font-style: normal&quot; title=&quot;Psalm 82:2–5&quot; class=&quot;bibleref&quot;&gt;verses 2–5&lt;/cite&gt;), a situation that will become the cause of their downfall. Their exalted status will be revoked and they will die like human beings (&lt;cite style=&quot;font-style: normal&quot; title=&quot;Psalm 82:6–7&quot; class=&quot;bibleref&quot;&gt;verses 6–7&lt;/cite&gt;). The psalmist speaks in his own voice in the &lt;cite style=&quot;font-style: normal&quot; title=&quot;Psalm 82:8&quot; class=&quot;bibleref&quot;&gt;final verse&lt;/cite&gt;, pleading for God to execute this judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a tradition that probably dates to the Second Temple period,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Psalm 82:6 had come to be read by some Jews as referring either to the giving of the Law at Sinai or to the exalted status of the first humans. &lt;cite style=&quot;font-style: normal&quot; title=&quot;Psalm 82:7&quot; class=&quot;bibleref&quot;&gt;Verse 7&lt;/cite&gt; was interpreted as referring either to the incident involving the Golden Calf or to Adam’s transgression. Verse 1, on the other hand, was taken to be an account of the &lt;em&gt;coming&lt;/em&gt; judgment, where the assembly of ‘gods’ could refer either to an angelic council or to the community of saved persons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When understood in this sense as envisioning the future community of saved persons, the image of the assembly of gods in Psalm 82:1 (TNIV) implies the restoration &lt;em&gt;in the end&lt;/em&gt; of something that was somehow lost &lt;em&gt;in the beginning:&lt;/em&gt; a filial relationship with God. A few short lines thus transform the biblical theme of fall and restoration into a drama of apocalyptic dimensions. It is no wonder that aspects of this tradition show up in sectarian literature like 11QMelchizedek (from the Dead Sea Scrolls) and the Gospel of John.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Gospel of John, Jesus quotes the first half of &lt;span class=&quot;noTag&quot;&gt;Psalm 82:6&lt;/span&gt; during a dispute with some disgruntled Judeans who had accused him both of blasphemy and of making himself out to be God (John 10:33–34). Interestingly enough, he introduces the quotation as though it belongs to the Law, a curious error if “Law” refers strictly to the five books of Moses (Genesis–Deuteronomy). Either he is using the term “Law” rather loosely, or, what seems more likely in view of the apocalyptic tradition sketched above, his introduction of the quotation as &lt;em&gt;coming from&lt;/em&gt; the Law already reflects a particular reading of the Psalm as a &lt;em&gt;commentary on&lt;/em&gt; the Law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gist of Jesus’ argument is that he ought not be accused of blasphemy for claiming the title “Son of God” when scripture indicates that those to whom the word of God came (in Eden? at Sinai?) were not only called “sons of the Most High” (in the portion of the psalm that he does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; quote), but even ‘gods’. His remark that “the scripture cannot be broken” anticipates the objection that his quotation does not actually come from the Law. In effect, he preempts such an objection by reminding his opponents of what is presumably their own view: that the Law and the Psalms belong to a unitary whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emphasis on Jesus’ &lt;em&gt;works&lt;/em&gt; in the framing verses cleverly plays on an ancient commonplace assumption that one’s deeds should match one’s words (John 10:32; 37–38). Jesus basically tells his opponents that his works confirm his claim to the title “Son of God,” but readers familiar with the Gospel of John may detect the irony in this response. John does not indicate that Jesus’ claim to divine sonship is legitimate merely because the word of God &lt;em&gt;came&lt;/em&gt; to him and is proven by his works. John signals from the beginning that Jesus &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the word and that the word &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; God (John 1:1), a claim that Jesus echoes in the statement “I and the Father are one” (&lt;span class=&quot;noTag&quot;&gt;John 10:30&lt;/span&gt;).&amp;lt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony of Jesus’ remarks in John 10 escapes his opponents, who lack the wider perspective afforded to the Gospel’s readers. In their rush to bring charges against him, his opponents not only fail to see that the word of God has come to them, they also fail to perceive the apocalyptic implication of this event: the way is now open for &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; become ‘gods’ and “sons of the Most High.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Readers steeped in the theology of the creeds may fail, in similar fashion, to observe that Jesus’ claim to divine sonship in John 10 is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; exclusive. Even if he is the only &lt;em&gt;begotten&lt;/em&gt; Son of God, all those to whom he comes can be &lt;em&gt;made&lt;/em&gt; ‘gods’ and sons of the Most High by the power of his word (compare the emphasis on divine speech in Psalm 82:6 to the near-rhythmic outbursts of divine speech in &lt;cite style=&quot;font-style: normal&quot; title=&quot;Genesis 1:1–2:4&quot; class=&quot;bibleref&quot;&gt;Genesis 1&lt;/cite&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that informed critics of the Orthodox theosis tradition would not disagree with this conclusion, but they might remain suspicious of the role accorded to &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt; effort in the tradition. I’ll have more to say about such criticisms later. For now my point is to indicate that &lt;span class=&quot;noTag&quot;&gt;Psalm 82:6&lt;/span&gt; is much more than an ad hoc prooftext. If we maintain that the patristic concept of “becoming god” arose organically from exegesis of Psalm 82 then we ought also appreciate the observation that at least one Jewish tradition—in which the earliest Christians (and arguably Jesus himself) participated—&lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; read Psalm 82 as concise and authoritative commentary on the biblical theme of fall and restoration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up: &lt;a href=&quot;/thoughts-on-theosis-part-3&quot;&gt;Theosis and Orthodox Doctrine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Including Athanasius’ preferred term, &lt;em&gt;theopoiesis.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;No less an evangelical luminary than J. I. Packer once suggested that Peter’s amanuensis (scribe) was prone to embellishment—an easy but problematic dismissal of &lt;span class=&quot;noTag&quot;&gt;2 Peter 1:4&lt;/span&gt; (“‘Outside the Church There is No Salvation’: An Orthodox and Evangelical Exchange,” discussion sponsored by the Society for the Study of Eastern Orthodoxy and Evangelicalism, St. Paul’s Orthodox Church, Irvine, CA, 1999). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Important exceptions include the Alexandrians—Origen, Athanasius, and Cyril—and, much later, the Athonite monk and Archbishop of Thessaloniki, Gregory Palamas (Norman Russell, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Fellow-Workers-God-Orthodox-Foundations/dp/0881413399?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=sacrveil-20&amp;amp;link_code=btl&amp;amp;camp=213689&amp;amp;creative=392969&quot;&gt;Fellow Workers With God: Orthodox Thinking on Theosis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 65–69). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Carl Mosser, “The Earliest Patristic Interpretations of Psalm 82, Jewish Antecedents, and the Origin of Christian Deification,” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Theological Studies&lt;/em&gt; 56.1 (2005): 30–73. Mosser has provided &lt;a href=&quot;http://jts.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/56/1/30?ijkey=MVYy5AKqzoJZkgZ&amp;amp;keytype=ref&quot;&gt;a link to his article&lt;/a&gt;. Non-specialists may find it a tough slog, but worth the effort. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2010 15:57:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-2</guid>
        
        <category>Psalms</category>
        
        <category>Participation in God</category>
        
        <category>John</category>
        
        <category>Deification</category>
        
        <category>2 Peter</category>
        
        <category>Jesus</category>
        
        <category>Theosis</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Orthodox Christianity is not Exotic</title>
        <description>&lt;!--excerpt.start--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Eastern Orthodox Christianity is most likely to feature in mass media at this time of year, the following remarks by John Anthony McGuckin are worth repeating, both for the benefit of Orthodox and non-Orthodox alike.&lt;!--excerpt.end--&gt; First, from McGuckin’s recent introduction to the Orthodox Church:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Orthodox (generally) do not regard themselves as exotic. If they have come to Orthodoxy from other forms of Western Christian tradition, or from secular atheism, they are often tempted to regard themselves as exotic for a while, but it soon wears off. Apparently, however, many external observers do still retain that perspective, and it can often tempt the Orthodox to live up to it by ‘posing’ as exotic: a dangerous state of affairs which postcolonial theory has put its finger on already as ‘subalternism’, or that state where a small group with a residual minority consciousness tries to live up to expectations foisted on it by the dominant hegemonic powers of the age. The Christian Orthodox, as they have been encountered relatively rarely, ‘in the flesh’, in the ordinary experience of most Western Christians, are certainly a ‘strange encounter’. The root presuppositions, and the basic style of worship and attitude that are so familiar in many forms of Western Christian practice, seem different here. If the Orthodox feature in the public eye of the media at all, it is usually with a view to the ‘strange’ rituals of a church that has a very ancient liturgical style, and often uses languages that outsiders do not remotely understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The temptation to categorize the Eastern Orthodox as romantically exotic is a powerful one, and is often a fate wished on them by those who hold them in kind regard and who value many of the things Orthodoxy represents in Christian history, such as faithfulness to tradition, endurance under suffering, and reverence in worship. Those who are less enamoured of Orthodoxy look at it from the perspective of their own philosophies, ideologies, and orthodoxies, and sometimes censure it as reactionary, exclusive, patriarchal, rigid in its doctrines and liturgy. Rarely, however, do either its critics who dislike it, or its non-Orthodox friends who cherish it, have much awareness of the wider context of what an Orthodox articulation of church and society would be on its own terms (&lt;em&gt;The Orthodox Church: An Introduction to its History, Doctrine, and Spiritual Culture&lt;/em&gt; [Malden, Mass.: Blackwell, 2008], p.1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, from Fr. McGuckin’s contribution to the &lt;em&gt;Festschrift&lt;/em&gt; honoring the late Jaroslav Pelikan on his eightieth birthday:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘We of the East … ’ is a phrase often associated with spokespersons of the Orthodox Christian Church in our age, one of such vastly increased intellectual mobility and ease of informational transmission that the theologians of the past (not excepting many in the present) would have been rendered dumb in the face of it (if such a thing is conceivable for a theologian). Compared to the era when one of the students of Evagrius would have meditated for a week on a couplet from the &lt;em&gt;Sententiae,&lt;/em&gt; we now have the capacity in the same time to read, or at least to peruse, books, journals, and ephemera; to see visual iconic forms flashed at us that collectively amount to more literature and far more symbols than an educated ancient might ever have processed in a lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the bewildering intellectual welter so grandly shored up by the gimcrack nomenclature of “postmodernism,” the phrase, “We of the East” floats reassuringly across the mental horizon, proceeds in stately fashion like a duchess crossing the carpet. It usually precedes an attempt to explain something of our religious identity as Orthodox, in reference to, or more usually in contradistinction from, the more common matrices of Western European Catholicism or Protestant experience. It has a fine cachet, though one that loses much of its shine when the “East” in question turns out to be the East End of London, East Pennsylvania, or the East Village of New York, places where one today is more likely to encounter Orthodox who are engaged in ecumenical dialogue with “the West” than in some putative Orient of our imagination” (“&lt;a href=&quot;http://books.google.ca/books?id=13DRvCcJUvcC&amp;amp;lpg=PA23&amp;amp;dq=%22Orthodoxy%20and%20Western%20Culture%22&amp;amp;pg=PA85#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;Orthodoxy and Western Christianity: The Original European Culture War?&lt;/a&gt;,” in ed. Valerie Hotchkiss and Patrick Henry, &lt;em&gt;Orthodoxy and Western Culture: A Collection of Essays Honoring Jaroslav Pelikan on His Eightieth Birthday&lt;/em&gt; [Crestwood, NY: St. Vladimir’s Seminary Press, 2005], p. 86).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2010 21:50:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/orthodox-christianity-is-not-exotic</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/orthodox-christianity-is-not-exotic</guid>
        
        <category>Orthodoxy</category>
        
        <category>Postcolonialism</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on Theosis, Part 1: Vocabulary</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Other posts in this series:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-2&quot;&gt;Part 2: What the Bible Says About Theosis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-3&quot;&gt;Part 3: Theosis and Orthodox Doctrine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In view of the recent surge of Protestant interest in the Orthodox understanding of theosis, especially among Evangelicals, I thought I would pull together a few remarks on the subject, with the caveat that the views and opinions expressed in what follows distill my own scarcely comprehensive reading and imperfect (in)experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although contemporary Orthodox Christians see themselves as heirs and transmitters of the Patristic and Byzantine tradition, reading the Church Fathers can be intimidating at first; the amount of material to sift through is immense, the learning curve is steep, and the most accessible translations are sometimes incomplete or outdated. Fortunately, Norman Russell’s Fellow Workers with God now provides a clear and readable primer on “Orthodox thinking on Theosis.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A glance at some of the older, still influential surveys of Orthodox Christianity illustrates why Russell’s contribution is important. Let’s start with the vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular introductions to Orthodoxy and surveys of Orthodox theology do not always include clearly marked chapters dedicated to theosis.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If they provide indices they may not include an entry for theosis or, if they do, it will likely point back to the entry for deification. In addition to theosis and deification, readers will also encounter more complex phrases that generally seem to cover the same territory, like union with God or participation in God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deification and theosis are basically synonyms. I’m not entirely sure what combination of factors has influenced an increasing preference for theosis among Orthodox theologians over the past decade or so,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but I would guess that the flowering of eastern patristic and Byzantine scholarship in the past century, initiated by Russian émigrés like Vladimir Lossky, Georges Florovsky, and John Meyendorff, has encouraged Orthodox theologians both to use the language of the Fathers and to distinguish their views from western conceptions of deification.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is also possible that, in their encounters with Evangelicals, the Orthodox have found that theosis does not set off Evangelical warning bells quite so quickly as deification.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt.start--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether union with God and participation in God are basically equivalent to theosis depends on whether one views theosis as the goal of human life (“union”) or as a process (“participation”).&lt;!--excerpt.end--&gt; As of this post, the Wikipedia article on “Theosis” tends toward the former, describing theosis as only the final stage of a three-stage process leading to union with God. Russell remarks, however, that theosis is both … and.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a certain unresolved but vital tension between these two aspects of theosis. Again, my guess is that Protestants’ fear of theosis is sometimes confirmed by their reading of Orthodox theologians who emphasize theosis as the goal of Christian life, which can be (partially correctly) interpreted as implying that theosis is something for which one must work. Theosis as a process may have more in common with what Protestants typically think of as sanctification. In either case a number of qualifications are necessary to prevent Orthodox thinking on theosis from sliding into pantheism or undifferentiated monotheism. Before we go there, however, stay tuned for a look at &lt;a href=&quot;/thoughts-on-theosis-part-2&quot;&gt;what the Bible says about Theosis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of scholarly books and essays on the subject, including Russell’s indispensible study ofThe Doctrine of Deification in the Greek Patristic Tradition Andrew Louth’s short essay on “The Place of Theosis in Orthodox Theology” is among the more accessible treatments (pp. 32–44 in Partakers of the Divine Nature: The History and Development of Deification in the Christian Traditions, edited by Michael J. Christensen and Jeffery A. Wittung). The full text of the late Panagiōtēs K. Chrēstou’s Partakers of God is available here. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Exceptions include Vladimir Lossky’s The Mystical Theology of the Eastern Church, with a chapter on “The Way of Union,” and Daniel Clendenin’s Eastern Orthodox Christianity: A Western Perspective, with a chapter entitled “The Deification of Humanity: Theosis.” In what is still the most popular introduction to Orthodoxy, Timothy (Metropolitan Kallistos) Ware’s The Orthodox Church, Ware discusses deification in a subsection entitled ‘Partakers of the Divine Nature’ (the links will take you to an older edition; my printed 1997 edition has been revised to incorporate inclusive language, among other things—“humankind” instead of “man”, etc.). So, the issue is not whether Orthodox theologians discuss theosis, inevitably they do, but how they define and present it (see note 6 below). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This shift can be observed quite clearly in the successive editions of a short book by Archimandrite George, Abbot of St. Gregorios Monastery on Mt. Athos. In three editions from 1992 to 2001, the English version was entitled The deification as the purpose of man’s life. The title of the most recent 2006 edition is Theosis: the true purpose of human life (note also the use of inclusive language). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Although the language of the Fathers is not necessarily uniform, at least initially. Carl Mosser has recently recommended using theopoiesis instead of theosis to characterize the perspective of early Church Fathers like Irenaeus, Athanasius, and others. For quick reference, Peter J. Leithart has provided a summary of Mosser’s views. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As a transliterated Greek word, theosis has both a technical ring and the quality of being what Mosser (see note 4 above) might call “an exotic flower.” See Mosser’s exchange with Michael J. Gorman in the comments section of Gorman’s Cross Talk post on Protestants’ Fear of Theosis. Mosser’s comments concerning my own criticism of his position are also worth a look. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In his introduction to Fellow Workers with God Russell quotes four contemporary Orthodox theologians, each of whom offers a different perspective on deification or theosis (pp. 19–21). These four perspectives can be classified according to two distinct emphases. Russell harmonizes these emphases in his description of theosis as “both the goal of the divine economy and the process by which the economy is worked out in the believer” (p. 21). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2010 11:44:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffkeiser.com/blog/thoughts-on-theosis-part-1</guid>
        
        <category>Participation in God</category>
        
        <category>Deification</category>
        
        <category>Union with God</category>
        
        <category>Theosis</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
